ours women are from venus
by dr john gray
[Music]
imagine that men are from mars and women are from venus
one day long ago the martians looking through their telescopes discovered the
venusians just glimpsing the venusians awakened
feelings they had never known they fell in love and quickly invented
space travel and flew to venus the venusians welcomed the martians with
open arms the love between the venusians and
martians was magical they delighted in being together doing
things together and sharing together though from different worlds they
reveled in their differences they spent months learning about each
other exploring and appreciating their different needs preferences
and even behavior patterns for years they lived together in love and harmony
then they decided to fly to earth in the beginning everything was
wonderful and beautiful but the effects of earth's atmosphere
took hold and one morning
everyone woke up with a peculiar kind of amnesia
selective amnesia both the martians and venusians forgot
that they were from different planets and were supposed to be different
and one morning everything they had learned about their
differences was erased from their memory and since that day
men and women have been in conflict without the awareness that we're
supposed to be different men and women are at odds with each
other we mistakenly assume that if our
partners love us they will react and behave in certain
ways the way we react when we love someone
men mistakenly expect women to think communicate
and react the way men do women mistakenly expect men to feel and
communicate and respond the way women do we've forgotten that men and women are
supposed to be different as a result our relationships are filled
with unnecessary friction and conflict clearly recognizing and respecting these
differences dramatically reduces confusion when
dealing with the opposite sex when you remember that men are from mars
and women are from venus everything can be explained
falling in love is always magical it feels eternal
we naively believe that somehow we are exempt from the problems our parents had
free from the odds that love will die assured that it's meant to be and we are
destined to live forever happily ever after
but as the magic recedes and daily life
takes over it emerges that men continue to expect
women to think and react like men and women expect men to feel and behave
like women we don't take the time to understand and
respect each other we become demanding resentful
judgmental and intolerant
we ask ourselves how does it happen
why does it happen why does it happen to us
to answer these questions our greatest minds have developed brilliant and
complex philosophical and psychological models
yet still the old patterns return and love dies
it happens to almost everyone very few people indeed are able to grow
and love yet it does happen
when men and women are able to respect and accept their differences
then love has a chance to blossom through understanding the hidden
differences of the opposite sex we can more successfully give and
receive the love that's in our hearts by validating and accepting our
differences creative solutions can be discovered
whereby we can succeed in getting what we want
and more important we can learn how to best love and
support the people we care about love is magical and it can last
if we remember our differences
the most frequently expressed complaint women have about men is that men don't
listen either a man completely ignores her when she speaks
or he listens for a few beats assesses what's bothering her and then
he proudly puts on his mr fix-it hat and offers her a solution to make her feel
better no matter how many times she tells him
that he's not listening he doesn't get it and he keeps doing the
same thing she wants empathy
he thinks she wants solutions
the most frequently expressed complaint men have about women
is that women are always trying to change them
when a woman loves a man she feels responsible to assist him in growing and
tries to help him improve the way he does things
she forms the home improvement committee and he becomes her primary focus
no matter how much he resists her help she persists
waiting for an opportunity to help him or to tell him what to do
she thinks she's nurturing him while he feels he's being controlled
instead he wants her acceptance these two problems can finally be solved
by first understanding why men offer solutions and why women seek to improve
let's pretend to go back in time and observe life on mars and venus
before the planets discovered one another and came to earth
we can gain some insights into men and women
martians value power competency efficiency and achievement
their sense of self is defined through their ability to achieve results
they experience fulfillment primarily through success and accomplishments
achieving goals is very important to a martian
because it's the way for him to prove his competence
and thus feel good about himself and for him to feel good about himself
he must achieve these goals alone by himself
autonomy is a symbol of efficiency power and competence
understanding this martian characteristic can help women to
understand why men resist so much being corrected
or being told what to do to offer a man unsolicited advice
is to presume that he doesn't know what to do or that he can't do it on his own
men are very touchy about this because the issue of competence is so
very important to them because he's handling his problems on
his own a martian rarely talks about his
problems unless he needs expert advice asking for help when you can do it
yourself is perceived as a sign of weakness
however if he truly does need help
then it's a sign of wisdom to get it in this case he'll find someone he
respects and then talk about his problem talking about a problem on mars is an
invitation for advice another martian feels honored by the opportunity
automatically he puts on his mr fixit hat
listens for a few beats and then offers some jewels of advice
this martian custom is one of the reasons
men instinctively offer solutions when a woman talks about her feelings or about
her problems when a woman innocently shares upset
feelings or explores out loud the problems of her day a man mistakenly
assumes she's looking for some expert advice
he proudly puts on his mr fix-it hat and begins giving advice
this is his way of trying to help and of showing love
once he's offered a solution however and she continues to be upset
it becomes increasingly difficult for him to listen because his solutions
being rejected he feels useless
he has no idea that by just listening with empathy and interest he can be
supportive he does not know that on venus talking
about problems is not an invitation to offer a solution
venusians have different values their sense of self is defined through
their feelings and the quality of their relationships and their communication
they experience fulfillment through sharing and relating
communication is of primary importance to share their personal feelings is much
more important than achieving goals or success
talking and relating to one another is a source of tremendous fulfillment
this fulfillment is hard for a man to comprehend
he can come close to understanding a woman's experience of sharing and
relating by comparing it to the satisfaction he
feels when he wins a race achieves a goal or solves a problem
instead of being goal oriented women are relationship oriented
they are more concerned with expressing their goodness their love their caring
venusians are very intuitive they pride themselves on being
considerate of the needs and feelings of others
a sign of great love is to offer help and assistance to another venusian
without even being asked because proving one's competence is not
as important to a venusian offering help is not offensive
and needing help is not a sign of weakness
a man however may feel offended when a woman offers advice
because he doesn't feel she trusts his ability to do it himself
a woman has no conception of this male sensitivity because for her
it's another feather in her hat if someone offers to help her it makes her
feel loved and cherished but offering help to a man can make him
feel incompetent weak or even unloved when a woman tries to improve a man he
feels she's trying to fix him she's trying to change him
he receives the message that he's broken
she doesn't realize her caring attempts to help
may actually humiliate him she mistakenly thinks she's just helping him
to grow without this insight into the nature of
men it's very easy for a woman to
unknowingly and unintentionally hurt and offend the man she loves most
for example tom and mary were going to a party tom
was driving after about 20 minutes
and going around the same block a few times
it was clear to mary that tom was lost she finally suggested that he call for
help tom became very silent
they eventually arrived at the party but the tension from that moment
persisted the whole evening mary had no idea of why tom was so upset
from her side she was just saying i love and care about you so i'm
offering this help from his side he was offended
what he heard was i don't trust you to get us there
you are incompetent without knowing about life on mars
mary couldn't appreciate how important it was for tom to accomplish his goal
without help offering advice was the ultimate insult
after hearing about martians and venusians
mary learned how to support tom at such difficult times
the next time he was lost instead of offering help
she restrained herself from offering any advice
she took a deep relaxing breath and appreciated in her heart what tom
was trying to do for her tom greatly appreciated her warmth and
trust the evening was a great success
generally speaking when a woman offers unsolicited advice or tries to help a
man she has no idea of how critical and
unloving she may sound to him even though her intent is loving
her suggestions do offend and sometimes hurt
his reactions may be strong especially if he felt criticized as a child or he
experienced his father being criticized by his mother
for many men it's important to prove that they can get to their goal
even if it's a small thing like driving to a restaurant or to a party
ironically he may be more sensitive about the little things than the big his
feelings are like this if i can't be trusted to do the small
things like getting us to a party how can she trust me to do the bigger things
like their martian and sisters men pride themselves on being experts especially
when it comes to fixing mechanical things getting places or solving
problems these are the times when he needs her
loving acceptance the most and not her advice or criticism
likewise if a man doesn't understand how a woman is different
he can make things worse when he's actually trying to help
men need to remember that women talk about problems to get close and not
necessarily to get solutions so many times a woman just wants to
share her feelings about her day and her husband thinking he's helping
interrupts her by offering a steady flow of solutions to her problems
for example mary comes home from an exhausting day
she wants and needs to share her feelings about the day she says
there's so much to do i don't have any time for myself
tom says you should quit that job you don't have
to work so hard find something you like to do
mary says but i like my job
they just expect me to change everything at a moment's notice
tom says don't listen to him
just do what you can do mary says i am
i can't believe i completely forgot to call my aunt today
tom says don't worry about it she'll understand
mary says do you know what she's going through
she needs me tom says
you worry too much that's why you're so unhappy
mary angrily says i'm not always unhappy can't you just
listen to me tom says i am listening
mary says why do i even bother after this conversation mary was more
frustrated than when she arrived home seeking intimacy and companionship
tom was also frustrated and had no idea what went wrong
he wanted to help but his problem-solving tactics didn't work
without knowing about life on venus tom didn't understand how important it
was just to listen without offering solutions
his solutions only made things worse you see venusians never offer solutions
when someone's talking about their feelings
when tom heard about the venusians and how much they needed to talk
he gradually learned how to listen when mary now comes home tired or
exhausted their conversations are quite different they sound like this
mary says there's so much to do i have no time for
me tom takes a deep breath relaxes on the
exhale and says
hmm sounds like you had a hard day
mary says they expect me to change everything at a
moment's notice i don't know what to do
tom pauses and then says hmm
[Music] mary says i even forgot to call my aunt
tom says with a slightly wrinkled brow oh no
mary says she needs me so much now i feel so bad
tom says you're such a loving person come here let me give you a hug
tom gives mary a hug and she relaxes in his arms with a sire relief
she then says i love talking with you
you make me really happy and as they finish the hug
she says thanks for listening i feel much better
not only mary but also tom felt better he was amazed at how much happier his
wife was when he finally learned to listen
not everything is wrong with mr fixit or the home improvement committee these are
very positive martian and venusian attributes
the mistakes are only in timing and approach
men need to remember that when women seem upset and talk about their problems
it's not the time to offer solutions women need to remember that unsolicited
advice or criticism especially if he's just made a mistake
makes him feel unloved and controlled to learn from his mistakes he needs to
feel her acceptance more than her advice when a man feels that a woman is not
trying to improve him he's much more likely to ask for her feedback and
advice if you're a woman i suggest for the next
week practice restraining from giving any
unsolicited advice or criticism the men in your life will not only
appreciate it but also will be much more attentive to your needs and responsive
if you're a man i suggest that for the next week you
practice listening whenever a woman speaks
with the sole intention of respectfully understanding what she's going through
practice biting your tongue whenever you get the urge to offer a solution
or change how she's feeling you'll be surprised when you experience
how much she appreciates you
one of the biggest differences between men and women is how they cope with
stress men become increasingly focused and
withdrawn while women become increasingly
overwhelmed and emotionally involved at these times a man's needs for feeling
good are different from a woman's he feels better by solving problems
while she feels better by talking about problems
not understanding and accepting these differences creates unnecessary friction
in our relationships here's a common example when tom comes
home he wants to relax and unwind by quietly reading the news
he is stressed by the unsolved problems of his day and finds relief through
forgetting about them his wife mary also wants to relax from her stressful day
she however wants to find relief by talking about the problems of her day
the tension slowly building between them gradually becomes resentment
tom secretly thinks mary talks too much while mary feels ignored
without understanding their differences they will grow further apart
problem can be resolved first by understanding in greater detail
how men and women cope with stress let's again observe life on mars and
venus and glean some insights about men and women
when a martian gets upset he never talks about what's bothering
him instead he becomes very quiet and goes to his private cave to think
about his problem mulling it over to find a solution
when he has found the solution he feels much better and comes out of his cave
if he can't find a solution then he needs to do something to forget
his problems like reading a magazine or playing a game
this is hard for women to understand because on venus
sharing your problems with another is an important activity and it's actually
considered a sign of love and trust when a man is stressed he will withdraw
into the cave of his mind and focus on solving a problem
at such times he is powerless to give his partner the attention
and communication she needs and deserves it's hard for her to be accepting of him
at these times because she doesn't know how stressed he
is if he were to come home and talk about
his problems then she could be more compassionate
but when a man is stuck in his cave a woman resents his not being more open
she feels hurt when he turns on the news or goes outside to play some basketball
and ignores her it's easy to take it personally
to expect a man who's in his cave instantly to become open responsive and
loving is as unrealistic as expecting a woman
who's upset to immediately calm down and make
complete sense on the other hand men generally have
little awareness of how distant they become when they're in their cave
as a man recognizes how withdrawing into his cave may affect a woman
he can be more compassionate when she feels neglected and unimportant
to increase consideration both men and women need to understand each other
better when a man begins to ignore his wife she
often takes it personally knowing he's coping with stress in his
own way is extremely helpful but does not always help her alleviate
the pain at such times she may feel the need to
talk about these feelings this is when it's important for the man
to validate her feelings he needs to understand that she has a
right to talk about her feelings just as he has a right to withdraw into his cave
and not talk if she doesn't feel understood then it's
difficult for her to release her hurt and accept his differences
when women talk about problems men usually
resist a man assumes she's talking with him about her problems because she's
holding him responsible the more problems the more he feels
blamed he doesn't realize that she's talking to
feel better a man doesn't know that she will appreciate it greatly if he will
just listen men become impatient when women talk
about problems in great detail he thinks that all the details are
necessary for him to find a solution to her problem
he struggles to find their relevance and becomes impatient
the more details she gives the more he's frustrated while listening
his frustration is lessened if he can remember
that she is greatly benefiting by talking about the details
this is something important to her something a woman can do to make it a
little easier for a man is to let him know in advance the outcome of the story
and then go back and give the details avoid keeping him in suspense
if a woman can remind a man that she just wants to talk about her problems
and that he doesn't have to solve any of them
it can help them to relax and just listen
centuries before the martians and venusians got together they've been
quite happy living in their separate worlds
then one day everything changed the martians and venusians suddenly became
depressed it was this depression that motivated
them eventually to come together understanding the secrets of their
transformation helps us today to recognize how men and women are
motivated in different ways with this new awareness you will be
better equipped to support your partner as well as get the support you need at
difficult and stressful times let's go back in time
and pretend to witness what happened when the martians became depressed
everyone on the planet left the cities and went to their caves for a long time
they were stuck and couldn't come out until one day when a martian happened to
glimpse the beautiful venusians through his telescope
the sight of these beautiful beings inspired the martians and they felt
their depression miraculously lift suddenly they felt needed
they came out of their caves and began building a fleet of spaceships to fly to
venus when the venusians became depressed
to feel better they formed circles and began talking with one another about
their problems but this didn't seem to relieve the
depression they stayed depressed for a long time
until through their intuition they experienced a vision
strong and wondrous beings the martians would be coming across the universe to
love serve and support them suddenly they
felt cherished their depression lifted
and they happily began preparing for the arrival of the martians
men are motivated and empowered when they feel needed
women are motivated and empowered when they feel cherished
these secrets of motivation are still applicable
when a man does not feel needed in a relationship
he gradually becomes passive and less energized
with each passing day he has less to give to the relationship
on the other hand when he feels trusted to do his best to fulfill her needs
and appreciated for his efforts he is empowered and has more to give
when a woman doesn't feel cherished in a relationship she gradually becomes
overly responsible and exhausted from giving too much
on the other hand when she feels cared for and respected
and special she is fulfilled and has more to give
when a man is in love he begins to care about another as much as himself
he experiences his partner's fulfillment as if it were his own
he can easily endure any hardship to make her happy because her happiness
makes him happy his struggles become easier
he is energized with a higher purpose most men are not only hungry to give
love but are starving for it their biggest problem is they don't know
what they're missing they rarely saw their fathers succeed in
fulfilling their mothers through giving when his relationships fail he finds
himself depressed and stuck in his cave he stops caring
and then doesn't know why he's so depressed
at such times he asks himself what is it all for
why should i even bother he doesn't know that he has stopped
caring because he doesn't feel needed he doesn't realize that by finding
someone who needs him he can shake off his depression and be motivated again
not to be needed is a slow death for a man
most men have little awareness of how important it is to a woman
to feel supported by someone who cares women are happy when they believe their
needs will be met when a woman is upset she needs to feel
she's not alone she needs to feel loved and cherished
empathy understanding validation and compassion go a long way
to assist her in becoming more receptive and appreciative of his support
men mendel realized this because their martian instincts tell them it's best to
be alone when they're upset when she's upset out of respect he will
leave her alone or if he stays he makes matters worse by
trying to solve her problems he doesn't instinctively realize that
what she needs most is just someone to be there
someone to listen someone who cares
a woman's tendency to become overly responsible
relaxes as she remembers that she is worthy of
love she doesn't have to earn it
she can relax give less and receive more
she deserves it when a woman realizes she's been giving
too much she tends to blame her partner for her unhappiness
although she has not received what she deserves to improve her relationships
she needs to recognize how she contributed to the problem
when a woman gives too much she should not blame her partner solely for the
problem likewise a man who gives less should not
blame his partner for being negative or unreceptive to him blaming does not work
understanding trust
compassion acceptance and support are the solution
not blaming our partners when this situation occurs
instead of blaming his partner for being resentful
a man can be compassionate and offer his support even if she doesn't ask for it
listen to her even if at first it sounds like blame and help her to trust and
open up by doing little things for her to show
he cares instead of blaming a man for giving less
a woman can accept and forgive her partner's imperfections especially when
he disappoints her trust that he wants to give more but he
doesn't know how or he doesn't realize how important it
is and so he doesn't offer his support she can also encourage him to give more
by appreciating what he does do and continue to ask for his support
most important however a woman needs to recognize her boundaries of what she can
give without later resenting her partner
instead of giving more and expecting her partner to then even the score
she needs to keep it even by regulating how much she gives
setting limits and receiving are very scary for a woman
she is commonly afraid of needing too much and then being rejected or judged
or even abandoned deep inside her unconscious
she may hold the incorrect belief that she is unworthy of love
particularly if as a child she witnessed abuse or was directly abused then she's
even more vulnerable to feeling unworthy of love
hidden in the unconscious this feeling generates the fear of
needing others because she is afraid of not being
supported she unknowingly pushes away the support she needs
when a man receives the message that she doesn't trust him to fulfill her needs
then he feels immediately rejected and is turned off
her hopelessness and mistrust transform her valid needs
into desperate expressions of neediness and communicate to him the message that
she doesn't trust him to support her ironically men are primarily motivated
by being needed but are turned off by this kind of neediness
at such times a woman mistakenly assumes that having needs turned him off
when in truth it is her hopelessness desperation and mistrust that has done
so without recognizing that men need to be
trusted it is difficult and confusing for women to understand the difference
between needing
and neediness needing
is openly reaching out and asking for support from a man in a trusting manner
one that assumes that he will do his best
this empowers him neediness however is desperately needing
support because you don't trust you'll get it
it pushes men away and makes them feel rejected and unappreciated
for women not only is needing others confusing but being disappointed or
feeling abandoned is especially painful even in the smallest ways
needing others puts her in a vulnerable position
being ignored or disappointed hurts more because it affirms the incorrect belief
that she's unworthy when a woman realizes that she truly
deserves to be loved she's opening the door for a man to give
to her but when it takes her ten years of over giving in a marriage to realize
that she deserves more ironically she feels like closing the door and not
giving him the chance when this is the case i have to assure
women that they don't have to give more to have a better relationship
their partner will actually give more if they give less
when a man has been ignoring her needs it's as though they have both been
asleep when she wakes up and remembers her
needs he also wakes up and wants to give her
more a man's deepest fear is that he's not
good enough or that he's incompetent
he compensates for this fear by focusing on increasing his power and
competence success achievement and efficiency are
foremost in his life just as a woman
is afraid around receiving men tend to be afraid around giving
to extend himself and giving to her means to risk failure
correction or even disapproval
these consequences are most painful because deep inside his unconscious he
may hold the incorrect belief that he's not good enough
this belief was formed and reinforced in childhood every time he thought he was
expected to do better ironically when a man really cares about
his partner his fear of failure increases
and sometimes he gives less to avoid failure he stops giving to the
people he wants to give to the most he appears most uncaring when he's most
afraid the first step for man and learning how
to give is to realize that it's okay to make mistakes
and it's okay to fail and that he doesn't have to have all the
answers the phrase i don't know isn't even in
the martian dictionary
women commonly misinterpret a man's silence
depending upon how she's feeling that day she may begin to imagine the very
worst he hates me he doesn't love me
he's leaving me forever this may then trigger her deepest fear
which is i'm afraid if he rejects me then i will
never be loved i don't deserve to be loved
when a man is silent it's easy for a woman to imagine the
worst because the only times a woman would be silent
or when she had something to say that would be hurtful
or when she didn't want to talk to a person
because she didn't trust him anymore and wanted nothing to do with him
no wonder a woman becomes insecure when a man suddenly becomes quiet
women have a lot to learn about men before relationships can be really
fulfilling they need to learn that when a man is
upset or stressed he will automatically stop talking
go to his cave and work things out and no one is allowed in that cave
when a man goes to his cave women should not become scared that they have done
something terribly wrong they need to gradually learn that if you
just let a man go into his cave after a while he'll come out and
everything will be fine it is important for women not to try to
get a man to talk before he's ready women get burned not only when they
unknowingly invade a man's introspective time but also when they misinterpret his
expressions which are generally warnings that he is either in his cave or on his
way when asked what's the matter
a martian will say something brief like it's nothing
or i'm okay even when a man's out of the cave he
still needs to be trusted they don't like unsolicited advice or
empathy they need to prove themselves
a man feels supported when a woman communicates in a way that says
i trust you to handle things unless you directly ask for help
learning to support men in this way can be very difficult in the beginning
many women feel that the only way they can get what they need in a relationship
is to criticize a man when he makes mistakes or to offer unsolicited advice
if he behaves in a manner that she doesn't like
she can directly tell him that she doesn't like his behavior without
casting judgment that he is wrong or bad without an understanding of
how she may be turning the men off in her life with unsolicited advice or
criticism a woman feels powerless to get what she
needs or what she wants from a man
nancy was frustrated in her relationship she said
i still don't know how to approach a man with criticism and advice
no matter how i tell him he gets angry or defensive or just ignores me
the answer is she should not offer criticism or advice unless he asks
instead she should try giving him loving
acceptance this is what he needs not lectures
men need to feel very secure before they open up and ask for support
as we've discussed when a man goes into his cave
or becomes quiet he's saying i need some time to think about this
please stop talking to me i'll be back
and then we can talk when he goes to his cave
a man doesn't realize that a woman may hear
i don't love you i can't stand to listen to you
i'm leaving and i'm never coming back to counteract this message he can learn
to say these four magic words
i will be back
i'll be back it's amazing how these simple words make
such a profound difference in addition he could say
i'll be back and then we can talk again good communication requires
participation on both sides a man needs to work at remembering that
complaining about problems does not mean he's being blamed
a woman can work at letting him know that though she's complaining sometimes
she also appreciates him or that she's not blaming him
for example while writing this chapter
my wife bonnie came in and asked how i was doing
i said good how's your day she said
oh there's so much to do we hardly have any time together anymore
the old me would have become very defensive and reminded her of all the
time we have spent together or i would have told her how important
my deadline was this would have just created tension
the newbie aware of our differences understood that she was just looking for
some reassurance and understanding and she wasn't looking for any
justifications or explanations i said
you're right we've been really busy it's been a long day come here sit in my
lap let me give you a hug she then said
you feel really good this was the appreciation i needed in order to be
more available to her i then offered to drop off the
babysitter so she could relax before dinner
she said really you'll take the babysitter home that'd be great thanks
again she gave me the appreciation i needed to feel like a successful partner
even when she was tired and exhausted women don't always think of giving
appreciation because they assume a man knows how much
she appreciates being heard he doesn't know
he thinks he's doing nothing by listening
when she's talking about problems he needs to be reassured that he is still
loved and appreciated and that he's doing something
even though from his point of view he's doing nothing but listening
men feel frustrated by problems unless they're doing something to solve
them by appreciating him for being a good
listener a woman can let him know that just by
listening he is also helping a woman does not have to suppress her
feelings or even change them to support her partner
she does however need to express them in a way that doesn't make him feel
attacked accused are blamed making a few small changes can make a
big difference the four magic words to support a man
are it's not your fault
it's not your fault reassuring a man that it's not his fault
or that he's not being blamed works only as long as she truly is not
blaming him if she is attacking him then she should
share her feelings with somebody else she should wait until she's more loving
or centered to talk to him a man often blames a woman for being
blaming when she is innocently talking about problems
this is very destructive to the relationship because it blocks
communication a helpful approach is to remember that
she always has a right to be upset and that once she gets it out she will
feel much better as a man learns to listen and interpret
a woman's feelings correctly communication becomes easier
although listening is an important skill to practice
some days a man is too stressed or too sensitive to translate the intended
meaning of her phrases at such times
he should not even attempt to listen instead he could kindly say
this isn't a good time for me let's talk about it later i need some time alone
as bonnie and i have learned to communicate in a way that respects our
differences and understands our needs our marriage has become so much easier
i've witnessed this kind of transformation in thousands of
individuals and couples relationships thrive when communication
reflects a ready acceptance and a respect of
people's innate differences when misunderstandings arise remember
that we speak different languages take the time necessary to translate
what your partner really means or wants to say
this definitely takes practice but it's well worth it
men are like rubber bands when they pull away
they can stretch only so far before they come springing back
a rubber band is the perfect metaphor to understand the male intimacy cycle this
cycle involves getting close pulling away
and then getting close again most women are surprised to realize that
even when a man loves a woman periodically he needs to pull away
before he can get closer men instinctively feel this urge to pull
away it's not a decision or even a choice it
just happens it's a natural cycle women misinterpret a man's pulling away
because generally speaking a woman pulls away for different reasons
she pulls back when she doesn't trust him to understand her feelings
when she's been hurt or she's afraid of being hurt again
or when he's done something wrong and disappointed her
certainly a man may pull away for the same reasons
but he will also pull away even if she's done nothing wrong
he pulls away to fulfill his need for independence or autonomy
when he is fully separated when he is pulled away
then suddenly he will feel his need for love and intimacy again
automatically he will be more motivated to give his love and receive back the
love he needs if understood this male intimacy cycle
enriches a relationship because it is misunderstood it creates
unnecessary problems let's explore an example
maggie was distressed anxious and confused
she and her boyfriend jeff had been dating for about six months
everything had been so romantic then without any apparent reason he
began to distance himself emotionally maggie couldn't understand why he had
suddenly pulled away she thought she'd done something wrong
after taking my seminar maggie realized that when jeff pulled
away it was not her fault in addition
she learned why he was pulling away and how to gracefully deal with it
months later at another seminar jeff thanked me for what maggie had learned
he told me they were now engaged to be married
maggie had discovered a secret about men that few women know
maggie realized that when she was trying to get close
while jeff was trying to pull away she was actually preventing him
from stretching his full distance and then springing back
by running after him she was preventing him from ever feeling that he needed her
and wanted to be with her she realized that she had done this in
every relationship unknowingly she had obstructed an
important cycle by trying to maintain intimacy
she actually had prevented it [Music]
when a man has stretched away his full distance
he will return with a lot of power and spring
this is generally puzzling for a woman because for her
becoming intimate again requires a period of re-acquaintance
if she doesn't understand that men are different in this way
she may have a tendency to mistrust his sudden desire for intimacy and push him
away men also need to understand this
difference when a man springs back before a woman
can open up again to him she generally wants and needs time and
conversation to reconnect this transition can be more graceful if
a man understands a woman may need more time
especially if she felt hurt when he pulled away
without this understanding a man may become impatient
a man automatically alternates between needing intimacy and
autonomy for example in the beginning of his relationship
with maggie jeff was strong and full of desire
he wanted to impress her fulfill her please her get close to her
as she opened her heart to him he got closer and closer he felt wonderful
but after a brief period a change took place
even though this closeness is fulfilling to man he will inevitably begin to feel
the urge to pull away having temporarily fulfilled his hunger
for intimacy like after a good meal
he now feels his hunger to be independent
or to go for a walk as jeff instinctively pulls away without
any explanation to maggie maggie reacts with fear
she feels powerless to get him back because she doesn't know what she did to
turn him off when she asks him what's the matter he
doesn't have a clear answer and so he resists talking about it
he just continues to distance from her even more
without an understanding of this cycle it's easy to see how men and women begin
to doubt their love maggie could easily assume that jeff
didn't love her without getting a chance to pull away
jeff would lose touch with his desire and passion to be close
he could easily assume he no longer loved maggie
after learning to let jeff have his distance
or space maggie discovered that he did come back
she practiced not running after him when he would withdraw
and trusted that everything was okay each time he did come back
as her trust in this process grew it became easier for her to accept this
part of jeff the more she just accepted him at those
times the sooner he would return as jeff began to understand his changing
feelings and needs he became more confident in his love for
her he was able to make a commitment without an understanding of how men are
like rubber bands it's very easy for women to misinterpret a man's
reactions when a man pulls away it's not because he doesn't want to talk
instead he needs some time alone time to be with himself when he's not
responsible for anybody else it's a time for him to take care of
himself when he returns then he's available to
talk to a certain extent a man loses himself
through connecting with his partner by feeling her needs
problems wants emotions he may lose touch with his own sense of
self pulling away allows him to re-establish
his personal boundaries and fulfill his need to feel autonomous
when a man is pulling away this is not the time to try to get
closer let him pull away
after some time he'll return he will appear loving and supportive
and act as though nothing has happened this is the time to talk
not when he's pulling away men generally don't realize how they're
suddenly pulling away and then later returning affects women
with insight about this intimacy cycle a man can recognize the importance of
sincerely listening when a woman speaks he grows to understand his own cycles
and reassures her when he pulls away that he will be back
when he returns to talk she might probe him to understand why he left
if he's not sure which is many times the case he might say
i'm not sure i just needed some time to myself
to initiate a conversation the wise woman learns not to demand that a man
talk but asked that he truly listened to her
as her emphasis changes the pressure on him is released
she learns to open up and share her feelings without demanding that he do
the same she trusts that he will gradually open
up more as he feels accepted and listens to her feelings
she does not punish him or chase after him
she understands that sometimes her intimate feelings trigger his need to
pull away while at other times when he's on his
way back he is quite capable of hearing her
intimate feelings
a woman is like a wave when she feels loved her self-esteem
rises and falls in a wave motion when she's feeling really good
she will reach a peak and then suddenly her mood may change
and her wave crashes down this crash is temporary
after she reaches bottom suddenly her mood will shift and she
will again feel good about herself and the wave rises back up a woman's
self-esteem rises and falls like a wave
when she hits bottom it's a time for emotional house cleaning
a woman's ability to give and receive love in her relationships is generally a
reflection of how she's feeling about herself
when she's not feeling as good about herself she's unable to be as accepting
and appreciative of her partner at her down times she tends to be
overwhelmed or more emotionally reactive when her wave hits bottom she's more
vulnerable and she needs more love it's as though she sinks down into a
well and in this well there are lots of
feelings and when they first come up they're not
clear it's crucial that her partner
understands what she needs at these times
otherwise he may make unreasonable demands
a man commonly assumes that her sudden change of mood
is based solely on his behavior when she is happy he takes credit but
when she is unhappy he also feels responsible
he may feel extremely frustrated because he doesn't know how to make things
better or he simply feels blamed mary and bill had been married for six
years bill had observed this wave pattern in
mary but because he didn't understand it he tried to fix it which made matters
worse bill said i can't understand my wife
mary for weeks she's the most wonderful woman
she gives her love unconditionally to me and to everyone
then suddenly she becomes overwhelmed by how much she's doing for everyone and
starts being very disapproving of me it's not my fault she's unhappy i
explain that to her and we just get into the biggest fights
like many men bill made the mistake of trying to
prevent his partner from bottoming out he tried to rescue her
he had not learned that she needed to hit bottom before she could come up
the last thing a woman needs when she's on her way down
is someone telling her why she shouldn't be down
what she needs is someone to be with her as she goes down
to listen to her for a while while she shares her feelings
and to empathize with what she's going through
even if a man can't fully understand why a woman feels so overwhelmed
he can offer his love he can give her attention and certainly
support her after learning how women are like waves
bill was still confused the next time his wife seemed to be in
her well or the wave had crashed he practiced listening to her
he told me at first i listened and she seemed to open up and cheer more
but then she started getting even more upset
it seemed the more i listened the more upset she got
i told her she shouldn't be getting more upset
and then we got into a big argument although bill was listening to mary
he was still trying to fix her he expected her to feel better right
away what bill didn't know is that when a
woman goes into her whale if she feels supported she doesn't necessarily feel
better right away she may even feel worse
but that is a sign that his support may be helping
his support may actually help her to hit bottom sooner and then she can and she
will feel better to genuinely come up she first needs to
hit bottom that is the cycle
when a woman comes out of the well she becomes her usual loving self again
this positive shift is generally misunderstood by men
a man typically thinks that whatever was bothering her is now completely healed
or resolved this is not the case it's an illusion
when her wave crashes again similar issues will arise
when her issues come up again he becomes impatient because he thinks
that they've already been resolved without understanding the wave
he finds it hard to validate and nurture her feelings
when she's feeling down or in the well when a woman goes into her well her
deepest issues tend to surface these issues may have to do with the
relationship but usually they are heavily charged
from her past relationships and childhood
whatever remains to be healed or resolved from her past inevitably will
come up as she feels more and more supported at
these difficult times she begins to trust the relationship
and is able to journey in and out of her well without conflict in her
relationship or struggle in her life this is the blessing of a loving
relationship to support a woman when she's in her
well is a special gift that she will greatly
appreciate gradually she will become free from the
gripping influences of her past she will still have her ups and downs
but they will not be so extreme that they overshadow her loving nature
men and women generally are unaware that they have different emotional needs
as a result they don't instinctively know how to support each other
men typically given relationships what men want
while women give to men what women want each mistakenly assumes that the other
has the same needs and desires as a result
they both end up dissatisfied or resentful
both men and women feel that they give and give but they don't get back
they feel that their love is unacknowledged and unappreciated
the truth is they are both giving love but not in the
desired manner most of our complex emotional needs can
be summarized as the need for love men and women each have six unique needs
that are all equally important men primarily need trust
acceptance appreciation
admiration approval
and encouragement women primarily need
caring understanding
respect devotion
validation and reassurance
certainly every man and woman ultimately needs all these 12 kinds of love
what is meant by primary need is that fulfilling a primary need is
required before one is able to receive and appreciate the other kinds of love
without an awareness of what is important for the opposite sex
men and women don't realize how much they may be hurting their partners are
depriving them of what they deserve women generally don't realize the ways
they communicate that are unsupportive and hurtful to the male ego
here's a list of three common mistakes women make in relation to a
man's primary love needs the first
she tries to improve his behavior or help him by offering unsolicited advice
he doesn't feel loved because she doesn't trust him
the second she doesn't acknowledge what he does for
her but complains about what he hasn't done
he feels taken for granted and unloved because she doesn't appreciate what he
does the third she corrects his behavior and tells him what to do as if he were a
child he feels unloved
because he doesn't feel admired through understanding a woman's primary
needs a man can be more sensitive to and respectful of her needs
the following shows three mistakes men make in relation to a woman's primary
emotional needs the first
he minimizes the importance of her feelings and needs
he makes children her work more important
she feels unloved because he's not devoted to her and doesn't honor her as
special the second
he listens but then gets angry and blames her for upsetting him or for
bringing him down she feels unloved because he doesn't
respect her feelings the third after listening he says
nothing or just walks away she feels insecure because she didn't
get the reassurance she needs many people give up when relationships
become too difficult relationships become easier when we
understand our partner's primary needs without giving more but by giving what
is required we don't burn out
to fulfill your partner you need to learn how to give the love he or she
primarily needs
of the most difficult challenges in our loving relationships is handling
differences in disagreements just as communication is the most
important element in a relationship arguments can be the most destructive
element because the closer we are to someone
the easier it is to bruise or to be bruised
for all practical purposes i strongly recommend that couples not argue
negotiate yes ask what you want express differences but don't argue or
fight it is possible to be honest open and
even express negative feelings without arguing or fighting
by remembering that we're from different planets
and developing good communication skills it's possible to avoid arguments
without suppressing negative feelings or even conflicting ideas and desires
it takes two to argue that only takes one to stop an argument
the best way to stop an argument is to nip it in the bud
stop talking and take a timeout reflect on how you're approaching your
partner try to understand how you're not giving
them what they need then after some time has passed come
back talk again but in a more loving and
respectful way time timeouts
allow us to cool off heal our wounds
center ourselves before trying to communicate again
men and women commonly argue about money sex decisions scheduling
values child rearing
household responsibilities these discussions and negotiations
however turn into painful arguments for only one reason
we're not feeling loved because women are not from mars
they don't instinctively realize that conflicting ideas and feelings and
desires are a difficult challenge for a man
the closer he is to a woman the harder it is to deal with differences and
disagreements when she doesn't like something he's
done he feels she doesn't like him
fulfilling a man's primary emotional needs will diminish his tendency to
engage in hurtful arguments automatically he'll be able to listen
and speak with much greater respect understanding and caring
most arguments escalate when a man begins to invalidate a
woman's feelings and she responds to him disapprovingly
when a man has done something to upset a woman his instinct is to explain to her
why she shouldn't be upset but when he explains himself
the only message she may hear
is that he doesn't care about her feelings
for her to hear his good reasons she first needs him to hear her good
reasons for being upset he needs to put his explanations on hold
and listen to her understanding her point of view
when he simply starts to care about her feelings
she will start to feel supported remember women need to feel cared for
men need to feel trusted this change in approach takes practice
but can be achieved generally when a woman expresses
feelings of frustration disappointment or worry
every cell in a man's body instinctively reacts with a list of explanations and
justifications designed to explain away her upset feelings
a man never intends to make matters worse
his tendency to explain away feelings is just martian instinct
the most common way women unknowingly start arguments is by
not being direct when they share their feelings
for example when a man is laid a woman may feel i
don't like waiting for you when you're late
or i was worried that something had happened to you
however when he arrives instead of directly sharing her feelings
she tends to ask rhetorical questions like
how could you be so late or why didn't you call
when a man hears a question like why didn't you call
he feels attacked and becomes defensive she has no idea of how painful her
disapproval in that moment is to him just as women need validation
men need approval most men are ashamed to admit how much
they need approval they may go to great lengths to prove
they don't care but why do they immediately become cold
distant and defensive when they lose a woman's approval
because not getting what they need hurts
one of the reasons relationships are so successful in the beginning is that a
man receives approval and rides high but as soon as he begins to disappoint
he's cast out into the dog house to treat a man as if he has no good
reason for what he does is to withhold the approval she so freely gave at the
beginning of the relationship a woman needs to remember
that she can still give approval even when she disagrees
every relationship has difficult times they may occur for a variety of reasons
like loss of a job death illness
or just not enough rest at these times the most important thing
is to try to communicate with a loving validating and approving attitude
in addition we need to accept and understand that we and our partners will
not always be perfect by learning successfully to communicate
in response to the smaller upsets in a relationship
it becomes easier to deal with the bigger challenges when they suddenly
appear
when we are upset or angry it is difficult to communicate lovingly
at such times even with the best intentions
talking turns into fighting in the heat of the moment we don't
remember how to communicate in a way that works for our partner or for us
at times like these women unknowingly tend to blame men and make them feel
guilty for their actions instead of remembering that her partner
is doing the best he can a woman could assume the worst and sound
critical and resentful when she feels a surge of negative
feelings it is especially difficult for a woman to speak in a trusting accepting
and appreciative way she doesn't realize how negative and
hurtful her attitude is to her partner when men become upset they tend to
become judgmental of a woman and her feelings
instead of remembering that his partner is vulnerable and sensitive
a man tends to forget her needs and sound mean and uncaring
when he feels a surge of negative feelings it's especially difficult for
him to speak in a caring understanding and respectful way he
doesn't realize how hurtful his negative attitude is to her
these are the times when talking doesn't work
fortunately there is another alternative
instead of verbally sharing your feelings with your partner write her or
him a letter writing letters allows you to listen to
your own feelings without worrying about hurting your partner
by freely expressing and listening to your own feelings
you automatically become more centered and loving
writing out your negative feelings is an excellent way to become aware of how
unloving you may sound because many times we don't realize how
unloving we sound with this greater awareness you can
adjust your approach it's easier in addition
by writing out your negative emotions their intensity can be released or at
least minimized making room for positive feelings to be
felt again having become more centered you can then
go to your partner and speak to him or to her in a more loving way
a way that's less judgmental or blaming as a result your chances of being heard
and understood of being accepted are much greater
instead of writing down your feelings you may also choose to do the same
process in your mind imagine in your mind you are saying what
you feel think and want without editing yourself
by carrying on an inner dialogue expressing the complete truth about your
feelings you will suddenly become free from their
negative grip one of the best ways to release
negativity and then communicate in a more loving fashion
is to use the love letter technique there are three aspects or parts to the
love letter technique the first write a letter
expressing your feelings of anger sadness
fear regret and love
the second write a response letter expressing what
you want to hear from your partner the third
share your letter and response letter with your partner
the love letter technique is quite flexible you may choose to do all three
steps or you may only do one or two of them
let's explore a few examples of how to write a love letter
address the letter to your partner pretend that he or she is listening to
you with love and understanding start with any angry feelings
then sad feelings then any fearful feelings
then feelings of regret and then love
include all five sections in each letter write a few sentences about each feeling
keep each section approximately the same length
speak in simple terms after each section pause and notice the
next feeling coming up write about that feeling
do not stop your letter until you get to the love
be patient and wait for the love to come out
sign your name at the end take a few moments to think about what
you need or want and then write it in a ps
use this guide in writing your love letters
in each of the five sections a few helpful lead-in phrases are included to
help you express your feelings you may use just a few of these phrases
or all of them generally the most releasing phrases
are i'm angry
i'm sad i'm afraid
i'm sorry i want
and i love however any phrases that assist you in
expressing your feelings will work it usually takes about 20 minutes to
complete a love letter here's a sample love letter that will
help you understand the technique jim was leaving the next morning for a
business trip that evening his wife virginia attempted
to create some intimacy she brought a mango into the bedroom and
offered him some jim was preoccupied reading a book in
bed and briefly commented that he wasn't hungry
virginia felt rejected and left instead of coming back and complaining
about his rudeness and insensitivity she wrote a love letter
after writing this letter virginia feeling more accepting and
forgiving went back into the bedroom and said
this is our last night before you leave let's spend some special time together
jim put down his book and they had a delightful intimate evening
writing a love letter gave virginia the strength and love to persist more
directly in getting her partner's attention
she did not even need to share her love letter with her partner
this is her letter dear jim
level one anger i'm frustrated that you want to read a
book and this is our last evening together before you leave
i'm angry that you ignore me i'm angry that you don't want to spend
this time with me i want to feel you love me
level two sadness i'm sad you don't want to be with me
i feel like you wouldn't even notice if i wasn't here
i don't feel special level three fear
i'm afraid you don't even care i'm afraid you don't like me
level four regret i feel so embarrassed wanting to spend
time with you when you don't even care i feel embarrassed getting so upset
i'm sorry if this sounds demanding i'm sorry i stopped trusting your love
and level five love
i do love you that's why i brought the mango
i wanted to spend some special time together
i forgive you for being so indifferent to me
i understand that you were in the middle of reading something
let's have a loving and intimate evening i love you
virginia p.s
the response i would like to hear
i love you virginia and i always want to spend a loving evening with you
i'm going to miss you
writing a response letter is the second step in the love letter technique
once you've expressed both your negative and positive feelings
taking an additional three to five minutes to write a response letter
can be a healing process in this response letter
you will write the kind of response you would like to have from your partner
imagine your partner is able to respond to your hurt feelings
the ones you expressed in your love letter
write a short letter to yourself pretending it is your partner writing it
to you include all the things you would like to
hear from your partner about the hurts you've expressed
the following lead-in phrases can get you started
remember this is a letter you're writing but pretending they're saying it to you
use these kinds of phrases thank you for i understand
i'm sorry you deserve
i want i love
sometimes writing a response letter is even more powerful than writing the love
letter writing out what we actually need
increases our openness to receiving the support we deserve
in addition when we imagine our partners
responding lovingly we actually make it easier for them to do so
some people are very good at writing out their negative feelings but have a hard
time finding the feelings of love it's especially important for these
people to write a response letter and explore
what they would want to hear in return be sure to feel your own resistance
about letting your partner support you this gives you an added awareness about
how difficult it must be for your partner to deal lovingly with
you at such times sometimes women object to writing
response letters they expect their partners to know what
to say they have a hidden feeling that says
i don't want to tell him what i need if he really loves me he'll know
in this case a woman needs to remember that men are from mars
and they really don't know what women need
they need to be told and gradually over time they'll learn
sometimes women ask me if i tell him what i want to hear
and he starts saying it how do i know he's not just saying it
i'm afraid he might not really mean it this is an important question
if a man doesn't love a woman he will not even bother to give her what she
needs if he even attempts to give a response
similar to her request then most likely he is really trying to
respond if in the beginning he doesn't sound
fully sincere it's because he's learning something new
it's awkward learning a new way of responding is
awkward to him it may feel weak
this is a critical time he needs lots of appreciation and encouragement he needs
feedback telling him he's on the right sharing your love letters is important
for the following reasons it gives your partner an opportunity to
support you it allows you to get the understanding
you need it helps couples to start talking again
when communication breaks down and it teaches us how to hear negative
feelings in a safe way
to receive more love we need to have people in our life with whom we can
openly and safely share our feelings a loving and supportive group can do
wonders to help us more easily get in touch with
our deeper feelings to share your feelings with a group
means there are more people available to give you love
i hope you will use this love letter technique because i've witnessed it
transform the lives of thousands of people including my own
as you write more love letters it becomes easier and works better it takes
practice but it's worth it when you want to feel better
write a love letter
if you're not getting the support you want in your relationships
a significant reason may be that you don't ask enough
or you may ask in a way that doesn't work
asking for love and support is essential to the success of any relationship
if you want a g-e-t then you have to ask
if you want to get more you have to ask more
both men and women have difficulty in asking for support
women however tend to find it much more frustrating and disappointing to ask for
support than men do on venus their motto is
love is never having to ask she may even purposefully not ask as a
test to see if he really loves her to pass the test she requires that he
anticipate her needs and offer his unsolicited support
this approach to relationships with men doesn't work
men are from mars and on mars if you want more support you
simply have to ask for it in the beginning of a relationship if a
woman doesn't get the support she wants she then assumes he's not giving because
he has nothing more to give she patiently and lovingly continues to
give to him assuming that sooner or later he'll
catch up he assumes however
he is giving enough because she continues to give to him
eventually she may ask for his support but by this time she is given so much
more and feels so much resentment that her
request is really a demand
men do not respond well to demands and resentment
even if a man is willing to give support her resentment or demands
will lead him to say no demands are complete turn off
the first step is to practice asking for your already getting
become aware of what your partner is already doing for you especially the
little things begin asking him to do the little things
he already does then when he does these little things
give him a lot of appreciation in this first stage don't expect him to
offer his support it's important not to ask for more than
what he's used to giving allow them to become used to hearing you ask for
things in a non-demanding tone just as a woman who is upset
doesn't want to hear a list of reasons and explanations about why she shouldn't
be upset a man doesn't want to hear a list of
reasons about why he should fulfill her request
simply be direct an indirect request makes a man feel
taken for granted or even controlled one of the most common mistakes in
asking for support is the use of the words could you
or can you in place of would you will you
to a man it makes a big difference if you say could you empty the trash versus
would you empty the trash to him he'd much prefer to hear would
you empty the trash the hardest thing of learning to ask is
remembering how to do it try using the w words whenever possible
it will take a lot of practice be direct
be brief and use would you
or will you phrases be aware of how many times you don't ask
for support become aware of how you ask and when you
do remember to be brief and direct
then give him lots of appreciation and thanks
don't let anything be taken for granted when he's used to hearing you ask for
his support without wanting more he feels loved in your presence
he feels he doesn't have to change to get your love
at this point you can now risk asking for more
let him realize that he can say no and still receive your love
when he feels that he can say no when you ask for more
he will feel free to say yes or no keep in mind
that men are much more willing to say yes if they have the freedom to say no
once you can graciously accept a no you are ready to assert your full power to
get what you want you ask for his support
and if he starts making excuses and resists your request
you don't say okay in this third stage you practice making it okay that he
resists but continue waiting for him to say yes
the art of assertive asking is to remain silent after you've made a
request after you've asked
expect him to moan or groan or scowl or growl or mumble or grumble
i call all of these the grumbles when a man grumbles it's a good sign
it means he's trying to consider your request versus his
needs you may be asking yourself why men are so sensitive about being asked for
support it's not because men are lazy but
because men have a greater need to feel accepted
any request to be more or to give more makes him feel that he's not accepted
just the way is by learning to ask correctly for support
in the martian way you not only help him to feel more loved
but you also ensure that you'll get the love you need and deserve
one of the paradoxes of loving relationships is that when things are
going well and we're feeling loved we may suddenly find ourselves
emotionally distancing from our partners or reacting to them in unloving ways
it's surprising one day you're loving patient accepting
and then the next day you become demanding or dissatisfied
your partner does something loving for you
and you find yourself resenting them for all the times in the past when he or she
ignored you or
you're attracted to your partner and then when he or she makes a commitment
you lose your attraction or you find others more attractive
you feel good about yourself or your life and then suddenly you begin feeling
unworthy or abandoned or inadequate
these sudden shifts are confusing yet they're common
if we don't understand why they happen we may think we're going crazy
or we may mistakenly conclude our love has
died fortunately there's an explanation
love brings up our unresolved feelings whenever we're loving ourselves more or
being loved by others repressed feelings tend to come up
they come up to be healed and released if we can successfully deal with those
feelings then we can feel much better and enliven
more of our creative and loving potential
if however we get into a fight and blame our partner instead of healing our past
we just get upset and then suppress the feelings again
for years we have suppressed our painful feelings
then one day we fall in love and love makes us feel safe enough to become
aware of those feelings love opens us up and we start to feel
our pain when a man's past comes up he generally
heads for his cave he tends to be overly sensitive and
needs a lot of acceptance a lot of space when a woman's past comes up her
self-esteem crashes she descends into her well of feelings
and she needs a lot of tender loving care
this insight helps you to control your feelings when they come up
understanding how the feelings of the past come up
gives us a greater understanding of why our partners react the way they
do it's part of the healing process
as you grow more intimate in your relationships love increases
as a result deeper more painful feelings may come up that need to be healed
deep feelings like shame and fear
to heal them we need to share them but we're too afraid to reveal what
we're feeling at such times we may feel depressed
anxious bored
resentful or simply exhausted for no apparent reason
these are all symptoms of our stuff coming up
and being blocked when deep feelings come up we project
our feelings onto our partner it is a paradox
because you feel safe with your partner your deepest fears have a chance to
surface when they surface you become afraid
and unable to share what you feel when this happens the feelings that are
coming up get stuck this is why people with even very loving
relationships may inevitably need the help of a
therapist understanding how our past continues to
affect our relationships frees us to accept the ebb and flow of
love to be successful in our relationships we
must accept that sometimes our hearts are full
and at other times empty we must not expect our partners to
always be loving or even to remember how to be loving
we must also give ourselves the gift of understanding and not expect to remember
everything we've learned about being loving
the process of learning requires not only hearing and applying but also
forgetting and then remembering again throughout this tape you've learned
things your parents could not teach you they did not know
but now that you do know please be realistic
give yourself permission to keep making mistakes give your partner permission to
keep making mistakes integrating this new wisdom of having
loving relationships is a new challenge you are a pioneer
expect to be lost sometimes expect your partner to be lost
use this guide as a map to lead you through uncharted lands
again and again next time you're frustrated with the
opposite sex remember
men are from mars and women are from venus
even if you don't remember anything else from this tape
remembering that we're supposed to be different
will help you to be more loving by gradually releasing your judgments
and blame and persistently asking for what you
want you can create the loving relationships
you want need and deserve you have a lot to look forward to
may you continue to grow in love and light
thank you for letting me make a